Okay
Hey good afternoon everyone good
So a couple of announcement to Pier 1 final submission again
Wednesday I'm sure you must have some
Metro checkpoint for pa1 right now
Double dare review quiz review quiz today
Good morning I hope everyone remember that
And they go to reading exercise night so I'm getting some emails
Can you might have forgotten about the reading exercise to make sure that you do your reading exercise before
For you come to class and that's the way you get the Disco
Lines from the reading and exercise
Ep2 will release on Thursday
Okay so the weather confusion on pa-18 Raider Plaza
I think last time when I discussed I told her I told you that
Left so if I tease is a type of authority that you did Aphrodite
You got a BS Dino
But that's not true so that's not correct so
What happens if I throw works on a container class right so we would like to think of
BST as a container of data some kind of data so when you dear friends
A Knight Rider on a container class it should return a data data type
Okay so when you if you have an iPhone BSD
No vsti territory when you need a friend said it should
What should return
What's your name
Yeah that data
Should I turn the data
So if you have operations standard output
The data has to overload the operator
Okay so before we begin any other questions
Next
Yeah because integer is holiday automatic writing
You can overload only for an object ID cannot Overlook native Native
Skylake Boolean or integer
Double
Any other question
The next programming assignment is significantly hard
So you should start right away
I want this significantly higher it's it's many steps okay if it
Simple if you think about it if you had if you know the concept that many
Stepside on Adelaide
Erica
Togo's 4227 time in Dallas
And mighty with Christ which is really important for. I hope you have some time from Alcatraz
We can get some and I think that reading exercise for multimeter
I guess I'm assuming that you have read
About motivator
Let me go through them
Okay so last time we were going through this big ol
Runtime analysis so we have big oversized big Peter versus big Omega
I am so we have all
Beta and Omega
So we had this piece of corn
So we wanted to find out what the Big O
Hard disk
What's the run time in Tampa Bay go to how do how do you work this
To try to compute the number of steps that they sell Garden computer
How to how do you find the number of steps we have to lose out on love goes through
How many times
End times
N
10 - 110
End times
0 - 2 + -1
Search a 10-1 times they open
In management and an X I'm kind of confused
Okay starts with theaters and times
Is it in - 1 + 10 - 1
Yeah I'm right okay I was kind of confused so
4 + -1 things okay
So the first time
What's the number of steps for this inner loop
For the first time when are you going to zero
When are you going to zero
This goes from
One
N - 1
Thanks a lot
That's what the first one
What's the second one
10 - 2
10-2 so tell me again
One red
Okay
So that is equal to
And into n minus 1 by 2
The what the Big O for this
That's the number of steps
Is equal to
N Square
Okay is it all off in
Can it be off into the profile
Elga
So let's think about Omega-3
And square
Kennedy in
Yes
Kennedy into the profile now
What are Tita
In square
Peter of M
No
Peter
Anthony Barr 5
No
Okay
So I think as big as the bomb
Omega is the lower bound Peter is the tightest boundary
That is both from upper side and Lower Side
If you have
11 squared and Omega Red Square then it must be mm square
Okay so this is
Not to confuse with
Different kinds of analysis letter if I want to ask for tequila questions
Four baskets in Alice
Are worth getting a little you think of this as worst-case situation
What average gas mileage
Each of this one time can be bounded by big ol big day today,
Celexa
Do this exercise
So this is big or challenge what's the tightest
Okay so we want the tightest big around for the core
How about
Okay 10 more seconds
One
Five six
7 8 9 10 stop
Wow that's a nice girl there
So many people said or off in
Similarly One login
Login to you have all kinds of answers
Okay let's do a group of thinking just talk for a while
And then we can do this again so mean why you can ask your English teacher if you have any
Confusions RTA
Why did you guys think
And Logan and Logan
Down right down with a piece of paper and see and computer
Yeah just do it do it
What's the first step Quest Loop
Give me later that are related to news but the first time it does the inner loop
How many Star between run do it and headed up to
Oh yeah I would encourage you to start actually
Using a pen and paper then only got it right if you just
Think aloud you might be wrong okay let's do it let's do another word
Now and see where you are
15 seconds to do it quickly
910 1 2 3 4
Five stamp
Alright so busy
Be as it is now but they never answer app
Nugget
So let's do it
So we have to lose
Okay
Tune-ups so let's think about how many times the inner loop runs for the first time
Second time
2N is equal to in by 2
The second time how many times does Louisville run
How many times
Invite to
Satin by two
Current time
And by 4
Uptown yoga
You got one right
So if you add this thing
What happened
This is actually less than 2 in
Okay
How is it to end
If you might have some series you're right one by two
So it's basically an
-1 divided by
What's a 1-1 by to find something like that
Figured out at home how you can finish that this is actually
2N
Alright let's do it again so let's say we have is here so if we have to time
We have two and less and less invite to class after 2
I know that there was a practice to as mine SF us
Now this whole thing
Will go away right in two
Now we have 2 N -1
Thank
Okay
Search
What is this the tightest Big O for this
The tightest Big O
If it's not the tightest it's is this okay
So that's okay that's not the tightest question
Isn't this an infinite Loop
Why there's no infinite Loop
When you start dividing by 2 and N is an integer
If you started it by tomorrow at some point of time and will be equal to
Zero
Nbc.com
When anyone won back to exactly zero
Okay
Mulan how long till this is a tricky question okay I'm playing tricks
How long does it take to find whether or not an element is
Sorted linked list
Okay
Remember tricky question
How long does it take
NS sorted linked list
Okay 5 more seconds
One two three
45 stop
Okay
That's some people who study
So I want to hear why people said who said he okay
For some it's old one
Saw the way you access this link this is from this point the right you cannot directly on them
Excessive
But you are right so for some it's worth one for which one is 12 one
For a constant number of a letter we have in the first few
If the numbers are the first relocation is 2 of 1
So far if you're searching one it's all of One
If you're starting to you can also think of that old one because not depending on the end it's too
Okay
It is
So here actually I didn't specify
I didn't specify whether you're looking for the worst case
Are the best gas
Are the average case
So there is not enough information
So I mean this is not to be confused with so we have
What's the worst-case right
Our best case
Are average gay
But this has nothing to do with
How
Recalculate
Ornate Omega or Tita
So for each one of them I can have it analysis done
Second Step what were the worst Kidz Bop
So you can have them what's the best case that you can have
Papa bondye Bon Appetit Owen
What's the average game you can have all of this analysis
So this is just something to think about right when you
Do analysis runtime analysis
So if I say what's the worst case
Runtime
For the tightest upper bound
Then how would you answer it
Open that's a worst-case Applebaum
At Westgate Bingo okay
Okay
Zenefits well let's see
So you already answered this
How long does it take to find whether or not an element in the sorted linked list in the bay
Okay so we're looking at the best case
And I will thinking about
The tightest upper bound here
So what's the best case
12 1
Okay so what happened in the worst case
CertiFit store dent
How long does it take to find
In the
Ruscus
For the tightest Applebaum
Okay
Select Staff
15 seconds.
Stop
Okay
So I am
Okay that's the worst case because
In which case you can
Go to the end
Set alarm in
So let's think about BST okay so we will compare PST with linked list
Time to fine
Is open in Westgate
In a linked list
Is the time to find better
Worse
Are the same in the worst-case 4bst within elements
Today's the PST and it's in English
So what do you think
Okay 5 more seconds one
Two
Three four
Stop
Arch I want to see
I want to hear why people and Cersei
Okay
Worst case if it's the same
Any other question and answer
So did you
Radiohead
So it okay let's let's hear something from the first yest would be better
Okay
Okay so I didn't specify whether the best the balanced binary search tree or not
So if I didn't specify
Addressing the whiskey
Super didn't specify a place in the worse case or worst case a PST can be like this
Saudis in Turkey wear
The worst case scenario it actually say
We respect to the big all they had the same
Worst-case running time
But if it's best if the Beast is balanced
Then which is better
Vsts better
How better I go today
Login
So what would average get so let's think about the link list
Okay
Wedding you are the linked list
And I am
We're trying to compute average case analysis
For the link list so how long does it take to find an element in average
So I would like you to write down in your pen and paper
And I think I will just go down the tutors we go down and it's our discussion is open
And then and will work okay
Thought star Computing start computing
Can-Am
We'll see how you guys do okay the uterus go down and then we'll see what people are doing it right
So did you compute
Why am I
3821 LK
You're okay
Do you compute
Jonathan average
Can an average be divided by 10
Can you do a vine-dresser channel English
Can you go buy me something in English
Snap it sequential I sent you
What kind of random acts as if you could just like an array you could do a binary search
The concept of linked list is like you
You have been accessed from one to other so the underlying implementation we don't really know sometimes
Lyrics by using a razor not right what is the length
Concert 112 that's okay
Let's see what you guys find out
Okay start boarding in five second of stop one
345 stop
FN gun
Why is the door open
Set up a research one we got one right
He got the second one how many operation to
Capital One
3 if you get the end on average
Mean why are we assuming that it
Which Keys would be equally likely
Okay so why do you think the average gas oven
Average of 10 over 2
Why is it in Novato
Okay
Okay is you mean so you're assuming that if he is equally likely
So if we didn't specify anything
We're going to assume that they are all equally like it
Velocify specify
The frequency of each key and I will say it one is hundred percent
Okay that's that's my distribution
Then it's different
Question
If wanted hundred percent what's the average game
No you could you could search 1000 times
Find how long on an average
Search 1000 times
On average
How how long do you get
Because I said 100%
You always 21
Equity all all of the keys and if I didn't specify they're all equally likely so they have
One by and chance right so you multiply with this
And you got the orphan
Connecticut
Okay let's move on
Unless you have any doubts
Okay so the average gases can be tricky
If you have done the reading for the best average gas analysis it's really too
So I read at home how it's done when will touch up on the house
You can do it like that in in very simple steps
Not going to the details the details are in the book
And I have to read the book
Throwing up to think about run time on average case
So let's think about this specific BST
So this for a specific BST and 1 BST here
Is in there looking for one of the element in the BST what is the average number of comparison you need to
Make to find an element
446 Pacific BST
Send this case the runtime is pencil equivalent to number of comparison remake
Okay 10 seconds
The one
Two
Stop
Okay
Why
Sexy assume that each key is equally likely
So you have
One here and then two and then three
The 1 plus 2 plus 3 divided by 3 is equal to 2
Tonight's party specific BST
The assumption here is that each key is equally likely
So that the two minutes options are we make when we tried to do this analysis
For the average gas the first one is at all keys are equally likely to be searched for
But that's all you have all of these different kinds of BST with three now
So you could
Have
All of these cases can deeply like Lincoln
After that second assumption
Second assumption is that
These BST are created using a particular interest and Order
A particular in certain order
So the next exemption would be all in certain orders are equally likely
If you insert the keys in a particular order you have a PST particular bsd111
Trinidad BSD
I was young that all keys are equally likely so that the
NN compute average and casing that specific tonight
Let's work out this specific case here so for the cases where is equal to 3
St Nicola tree what's the average number of comparison we need to
Define an element
In any BST with peanuts
So take a pen and paper and start Computing this and
We'll see how you guys do
Rehabs in ok
Star Computing and start voting in the mail
Simultaneously if you want
Nobody has any clue
How to start how do we start
Safari Street figure out the number of average number of comparison
And then later on we can put the total average
Okay
Sony computer the first one in last Light now
Do it for the second one third one
Portland
And then let's do an average of the whole thing
Okay
Ru computing
Are you confused
Hot
Okay let's start Computing today
All right before we start Computing let let me see what you guys did for 10 seconds for this
One two three four five
$0.10
Wow so you have a distribution
As many people said
Valletta let's try to compute so we'll do it again okay we'll do it again
So
Take your pen and paper and start Computing what's the number for the first one
For the second one
Okay the rest you do it yourself
Do it yourself and then we'll go out again
Okay so let's see 10 seconds
10 seconds
Cr123
5 top
Okay
Good
So let's do it
5 by 3
What's going on
My thing is not working
Henry
Factory Shoe
Okay good
So five by three for this
And this one is
I would say I like 16533
Set alarm 6 by 3
And then so eat
Each of these are equally likely and that the second and has a mission
3 / how many are there 1 2 3 4 5 6 2 1 by 6
X
Addison
Which is equal to
36 - 2/3 into 16 - 34 by 18
Okay
Good
Alright so let's say
So if you see the book
It's pretty a detail how you can do it for a general BST
And it's actually or login in average
You're not assuming that they are balanced
Bernard assuming that GST has to be balanced
So far all possible scenario
If you think about
Any insertion order
So in general if you do operations on a BST or regular beer
On average gas
It's really good
It's all login
But it was gas is baclofen
What gate is open but there's a big difference between love and in love login
When I have it it's it's really good
VST delay plugin
So go through the day analysis and the book and
You can see whites of login
Okay so for your programming assignment
Will compute the run time
And we won't compute by doing this kind of math
Answering compute by reading actual analysis L&M
Empirical analysis
Numerical analysis is basic level
Have a timer
When will actually have a clock
Why do Accord is running
We'll have a timer
And start the timer
And the end will stop the timer
And we'll figure out how long
The core will run
The first will enslave the data structure we don't want then it's late edition part
I want to see the runtime of a particular algorithm so before we start the garden
We
Start a timer
Okay
Then let the algorithm finish on a problem of size n
The end we can vary
The winning when we very end
There on time will change
Mac Daddy
Tell us how
The Bell Garden is performing on bigrentz
At the end of the garden will start the timer and then we compute the time
Okay so you'll be asked to measure your algorithm
Using this timer
On on your programming assignment
Okay
And you might have to turn in a report with some graph of this number
If you very end
How the rent IMAX weekend and you might have to come in till 9:40 o'clock case
In that situation
Yeah this is a demo and so I didn't and prepare the demo on the thing you can do
Do it yourself right so if you could do it on any piece of court
If you start looking at the programming assignment you wouldn't have even know how to start it
Timer how to stop a timer and have the computer run time
Okay
Alright
So for the PS2
You will Implement a dictionaries and an autocomplete
Today the checkpoint in for the checkpoint you need to implement insert and fine in it
To be really fast
The final commission is autocomplete and benchmarking service
This is where you start and stop your timer and figured out there on time
So you know what autocomplete is
Everybody knows where. Oh, so you going to implement an autocomplete function
Ever given a big dictionary so there will be a lot of words in the dictionary
So you can afford to look at all the words and suggest the autocomplete
You have to think of all the data structure
How to capture this and how to efficiently compute
First few frequently occurring words
Quickly
And then Benchmark Review times
So that two different data structures
BST
A hashmap and a try
To know about BST
And this week will go to the tie and the half man
Okay
And we compare the run times for all of the free dictionary
And we'll try to comment on how they perform engine
Okay
Davits gave the best skaters in the worst-case so that's up here too
And it's really challenging and all of these two different data structure
The start early
So let's think about tries so what is a try
Try is also a data center that is represented as
Just like BS test3
Different kind of tree
In it sometime it's called prefix trees or and Expressway
So eat snow inside this try doesn't contain the word
Searching for the whole word
It's more content
A part of the word
Answer for example if you have a binary try so this could be a word
In every note
Stores Only
One visit right 101 baked in this case
Okay so if you want to create the binary try for this
We have
Best friend so we start with
The root note
And we have a ward call 0 0 0 0 13420
Children
Create another note
Koala zero and Eleanor
Zero another note
How many zeros or Zeroes
4071 and then we create a note and remarked that note
Miso and I will Mark the North and it's
Basically a bit of lag on the note saying that it's a word that
Let me in
It's a word that is inserted in this latest update
So when we travel this when we find a note with this flag the blue color
Well I know that that would actually present in the Trap
So let's see if you can answer this we have couple of minutes so far this tribe does the
Structure of the tri depend on the order in which the keys are inserted
It's apt to try like this does the try the structure of the time depend on the Earth
Of insurgent
KP auto AC create different order does it
How come up with a different way
Okay few more seconds and 5 Seconds more one
2345 stop
Okay you could split so will discuss this next time