We're going to see how far we can get today let's just jump right into
Where we left off so we left off with this procedure called Explorer
We talked about how it would terminate right because
It's going to only encounter each vertex atmo
Most one time and it will never encounter or never visited vertex
More than one cell
Define number of vertices so it should terminate what I'm going to attempt to do now
Prove its correctness so to prove and algorithms correctness need to know what the algorithm is trying to
Does anybody know what the goal of Explorer is gay
Give me the graph and a starting for a text what do you want to happen
You want to set this visited value to be true for each
Vertex that is reachable from the starting for a text okay so
This is a proof technique that's used a lot in graph algorithms especially when
When you're talking about whether or not vertices are connected
I talked to does anybody know Russell from the CSE Department Heat
He calls this like the the first time failure proof method or something like that basically what we're going
Going to do is do a proof by contradiction
We're going to assume that algorithm doesn't work and figure out the first time it doesn't work and show that
There's a contradiction so we talked about
What the goal is so what would happen let's say okay let's do it with a say like this
What would what would we have to say would happen
The algorithm did work if the algorithm failed what we know to be true
That
A vertex
Oh oh oh right right okay
I thought it would be reachable but the algorithm wouldn't
Detective
Rides at the algorithm was not correct
What would write it wouldn't turn
This is this is how we're going to prove its the contradiction is going to be there exists a
You that is reachable from the but the algorithm doesn't
Set its value to be true
So if it's reachable from V that means that there exists a path from V2
To you
And since you is not true we know that be is true right that's just the first
Part of algorithm it's said to be true we know he is true and we know you was not true
So there's a point in this past where we find the first time it's fall
We have this is true
This is false
Night so there's a first time that it's false let's just say the first time that it's fall
What is w
Everything's true up until that point
So we get to see it is we set a value to be true right
It was false initially so what happens after you set a Vertex to be true
Right you look at all of the notes right you you look through all of the edges that are
Adjacent to it and you check if they're visited
And if they're not visited yet then you explore them
So
W is a neighbor of Z so when we explore Z
The encounter w
WS Falls
So
We explore W and what's the first thing you do when you explore as you said it to be true
Frank suck
So I'm
Basically if she has been in
Explored
Then double you must
Beset
Two
And there's your contradiction
Any questions
Okay
So what do I say at some point see was that the true that you look through all the vertices including ww has not
Habitat the truth so you explore W instead it to true
Okay how long does it take well we
We in in the worst case we may have to visit all of the vertices right and every time you
Visit of vertex you have to look through all of its neighbors right so every time you're at a vertex
You have to do degree of the many
Steps and so does anybody know what this sum is
Yeah so this is a undirected graph
So they don't have any directions to the degree of V is just however many edges are incident with B
Everybody now
Two times because you
Okay so basically you have to visit all the eggs all the vertices
And you have to visit twice
Signs true to the vertices and then checks all of these edges when it is visited each birthday
This algorithm has a run time of Big O V plus
In this class we're always going to say this is Lenny your time okay so whenever I ask you to design
Graph algorithm that runs in linear time
This is what I'm looking for
So
Any questions
Okay
So what if we want to keep track of the pads
Right what what we've done so far is
Explore will set true to all the vertices that are reachable from starting for a text
But sometimes that's not
That's not so useful maybe you actually want to know how to get there right when we're looking at the May
Problem
Did you just run Explorer as it is all you're going to know is whether or not the bird can reach the tree
But what's more useful is to know exactly how to get there
Frank so we're going to introduce
A small piece of code it's an array of
We're calling it previous or pre and basically whenever you
Find a Vertex that hasn't been visited
You said its previous value to the vertex that came right before it
So what this does is it is it to find a tree we're going to see that in a minute
Okay so let's do an example
We're going to
Explore
G
Na we're going to start at 8
And I'm
In this class the default
Usually on my vertices are all alphabetical the default unless I say otherwise is that we're going to
To always go in alphabetical order if there is a choice
Okay so
Reset a to be true
Visited
A is true
That's this part
Now for each Edge Vu so for each Edge coming out of how many edges are coming
Amun-ra
3 in so we're just going to look through them
And we're just going to respect the alphabetical ordering so the first one we're going to encounter a
Be right okay so be has not been visited so we
Set previous
Abby
To be equal to a
And then
We explore
Gob
Right
Williamsport GOP you said visited
B2B true
And then you look through
The edges
Incident with B so what's the first and you look at
A husband visited so this this if statement you just don't
If you don't go to that condition
And then you
You move along to the next to the next Edgewood BC
So you said previous
5 C to PB and then you explore
I got this is a very tedious way of
Showing algorithm
Instead what I'm going to do is I'm just going to build the tree as we go okay
And the um
The previous values like the previous thing that's going to be shown by a tree
Chuseok so let's just go like that so we started we go to be
Beach XA it's been visited Beach XC so it's not been visited so put in
The triage so she is a dead end right so then you break out of the
Floor C algorithm and you continue looking at the edges of bee
So the next edge of being you look at Izzy
And then you look at
And then J
And then Jay looks at a butt has been visited so
So you break out of that Explorer
Is also a dead end cuz it doesn't have any other
New vertices
And also and we get back to B and B is also a dead end
Then you go back to a day now goes to f
F goes to
Gigi Hadid
Ideas a dead-end to go back to G and you go to H
Okay are there any questions about that
So here I do it little bit nicer
Alright so this thing is called a DFS tree or a DFS output tree if you like
And what do you notice about the difference between the DFX output tree and the original
Right so this is a tree and this is this actually has some Cycles in it right
Which means that there are edges that we've missed
What are the ages that we've missed
AJ rank
What else bti
Did it
PayPal right but those those are not
Does. Didn't even get discovered
But that's fine that's that's what we want our algorithm to do is is skip over those because those are not
Connected to the starting for text
Okay
So
These
These red lines are called back edges and the black lines are called tree edges
Okay so let me just say a few things about this
You can't you can't look at a graph and tell which ones are back edges you have to do that
Algorithm
Packages are dependent on
The output tree of the outer it okay so
Definition packages
Packages in an undirected graph that has been explored or edges and G that are not in the DFS tree
Update
So what do back I just tell you about the graph
There's a loop there's a cycle right so if you find a package there's a cycle if there's a cycle that you will
You'll find a package
And how do you know if an egg is a package
Is missing from the tree and so there's a few ways you can do it you could
You could eat eggs to be true or to be visited
As you go through the tree
And then go back and check if there are any edges that you've met
So that's how I would do it
Assign
Visited
Age to be true
If age
Is
What's a good for Trevor
During
Explorer
Then after
Check
Any
Visited
Age is false
What's up this is the this is a good way to figure out if there are any Cycles in the grass
3 questions
Aren't
So um
Notice of the other thing that it did was it only found one connect to component right and it left the other one
Unexplored
Is exactly what we wanted to do so that's fine
Go to examine the rest of the graph we need to restart the Explorer on the other connected components
If we really want to know the structure of the entire draft
Okay before we do that I wanted to give you kind of a little hint about one of the homework problems
So
Noticed that when you have your tree right when you have your
DFS tree if you remove one of the packages
The tree is still connected
And basically what the theorem it says is that if you remove the edge that's part of a cycle
Pendergrass stays connected
And if you remove an edge that's not part of a cycle then the graph will become disconnected
Cancel this
That's that's that's
This little thing this might help you on one of the homework problems
Okay so now we're going to look at another algorithm that uses Explorer
What the purpose of this algorithm is to do is to count the number of connected components
Pet Shop
We're just going to call this depth-first search and I just called it that because the
I'm just following the book this is what the book called.
Basically what it does is it initializes is this variable called cc
Distance for connected component
And what we hope that it does
Is go to the graph and count how many connected components there are
So by the end of the process CC will be equal to the number of connected components
Okay so let's look at this first weekend if she lies
Everything to be false
And then we Loop through all the vertices of the graph
The disjoint parts
So I'm it looks to the vertices so the first vertex you encounter it
It is not visited yet right because we initialize everything to befall
Sedan you increment CC
Right because you've encountered a new connect to component then you explore that protects and we all know what explorer
Or does it sets true to all the vertices reachable from that starting for a text
Right so then once Explorer is done
You continue along this
This Loop
Until you find
A Vertex that has not been discovered
What does that mean if you found a Vertex that is not been discovered that means that that vertex is not
Part of that first connected component that you've done
So then you increment Cece and your support
Let's look at an example
Remember we're going to
By default run through the vertices in alphabetical order
So first we set them all to be false
Let's just
Remember that in our heads and then the next thing we do is we start at 8
If a is not visible to oh yeah first thing we do the CCA is not visited
Rent
So you set a to be visited
Annual increment cctv1
Wright Venue Explorer
That's what we did this we did this and now we're doing this exploring we go to be
We got us
We go to a
Right
Go back to FB is a dead end
Is there a custody
Okay so that that was Explorer and now a
BF and have all been visited right the visited value has been said the truth
So then we go to the next vertex
With this look so what's the next vertex we look at
Be right
Missing a thank you
The next vertex you look at is B B has been visited
So this
Conditional doesn't do anything and you just move to the next vertex next for Texas C
She has not been visited so you increment CC
And you sexy to be able to true and explore sea
Okay now are we done now
What's up
Receipt
Yeah we explored see now what's the next thing it does it looked at
Right
He has been visited but does nothing it looks like he has been visited it does nothing it just goes
It finishes up looping through this lupier
Until I get to the end of the loop and then they'll go to them terminate
Yeah I guess
I don't know somebody somebody said a similar thing of another graph to
So now I think it's a
Supposed to be there I think it's just when I printed it it might have skipped that
Notation
I'll let you know the other the other thing that they caught
Okay so let's move along to another
Another addition to the Alberta?
So I'm just calling this TFS because that's what the book does DFS in general is just kind of like a
Concept the concept is you you explore the graph
By going as deep as you possibly can that's why it's called depth-first search
And so in some contacts you'll see that DFS is just Explorer
But in this book that were using they call DFS in this whole algorithm that kind of explores the
The whole track
Just kind of thought
AR convention
Alright so we're going to add another thing into this algorithm
Pre and post numbers so what you can think about for pre and post numbers is thing
Think about it as you're putting the vertices into a stack
And every time you do an operation the clock increments Okay so
Every time you put a Vertex on to the Stacked you would sign it a free number
And every time you pop over text off of the Stacked you would sign it it supposed number
So are you
Initialize the clock and you put these two
Subroutines in there
I wanted to
I want to do it like that sorry
Clock
Hotspot
And basically what it does is before you
Floor the vertex well
I can say that after you assign the vertex to be true then like right after you do that you would sign it spree number
Then you look at all of its ashes outgoing edges and explore all of that area and when you
When you're done with that you come back to that vertex and you assign it is supposed to
So let's look at an example
Oh I wanted to say something
Pre and post numbers they don't have much use in directed with directed
Undirected graph
We're really going to see them useful with directed graphs as you'll see in this next example
Okay so
We're running DFS on this
Okay song
Be the guy in the other class said that this
This is from ETA is not on the spot under
Is that right
Okay. If you guys are following from the slides posted on the website draw that edge
Okay so we're running DFS so we're going to set CC
Need to be zero and then we see a and we get a
Reset a to be true
And we assign like this
I'm going to write its post number on the left and it's free number on the left is posted on the right
A has assigned us a day with one right then you look at all of
The edges coming out of a
There's only one right
COC
You said that to me too
And then she has three edges coming up so which one do you look at first
B
PS3
Okay now he has to adjust coming out so which one do you look at first
Hey right hey has been visited
So You Move Along 2
Okay so she is a dead end
Rent so you basically that means you're going to pop the out of the stack so what we've done so far as we put
A on the Stacked and see that be the DD is it dead-ends you pop the out and you a sign it is
Post number of 5B is also at 10:10 so you pop that out
Penske has still a few places to go right there you're not done exploring C
So you don't pop it out yet
So you go to
Can you assign it a pre number of 7
And then the next one is f
Episode dead end sign
G10
And then
Pretty much done so I just signed the post numbers 1213
14 15 16
Any questions
So I want you guys to try this
Again if you're looking at the slides then draw in this this Edge from U2
Now run DFS on here
But I want you to look through the at the vertices in Reverse alphabetical order keep track of the pre
Compose numbers and keep track of the CC variable
So I should see you should start out something like this species
Hero then we're going in reverse alphabetical order so we're starting with h
Can you assign the first pre number to be one
Tomorrow I'm going to start doing it if so we can follow
Which goes to
Two
Today
Three
Okay and then
Sexiest women
Did the next one is G
Okay is that what you guys got
So notice a few things about this the clock keeps
I'm going right it doesn't stop when you jump it doesn't reset when you jump to a new connected component
And what are we noticed about connect this is a variable connected components
CC
Is not very useful for directed graphs is it
I mean
We were really interested in information where it doesn't depend on the order that you
That you love
Encounter the vertices
Maybe just showed right that given two different ordering
One of them we got one connected component one of them we got three connected components oh
The conclusion here is that for directed graph this CC variable
Doesn't tell you the number of connected components racing
His face it doesn't really give a lot of information we're going to see how to use it to our advantage
Probably starting on Wednesday
But for right now it doesn't have much meaning
Are there any questions
Alright so let's go back to
The first graph we did now
Are there any edges that we missed
Let's see
ETA
Right
C to F
F.2d
What is a eth
H2 app
BJ
Okay I think that's it
Right
So just like with undirected graph right
When you do your DFS output tree there are certain edges that you missed right because
You have a graph and turning it into a tree
But with directed graph there are three different kinds of edges that are not part of the
Output tree
Okay there are things called
Packages
Forward edges
Ben Cross edges
Again these are just like the labeling of these age
This is completely determined by the algorithm right
You'll see that
An edge might be a package on this TFS output tree but all in
Slide when we did it the reverse way it may not be a package rights up to Define
Something as a back as you first have to construct the DFS output tree
Okay so what are the
What are the definitions of these three things
A package goes from a descendant to ancestor
A forward Edge goes from an ancestor to a descendant and a cross Edge goes
The cross-eyed you're just another
Forward or back
I mean
It looks like
From from F to D that's like a
That would be like a cousin right
This is the parents because Ian BR Brothers
Sisters
And the children of B&E are cuz it's okay what about from H2 app
That would be like a
Uncle right so if it's not grandpa or granddaughter or
Something like that then it's a cross Edge
Questions
I'm glad I'm glad you asked that
What are the uses of back Edge forward Edge and cross stitch
There's no use for cross edges or forward edges
Packages tell you something about the graph
Right
What what is it that they tell you
If there's a cycle forward edges and cross edges they don't really tell you much
And tell you
A lot of packages are the ones that are important
But I needed to classify them all so that we can tell the difference
Okay so um
Let's see here
What were the ages that we missed here
C to F
These guys aren't even related cute that's a package
B2d
BJ
I see that I did that c2e
E2f
Eth
G2g
NG th
Pizza
We have so that we may not even get the same number of packages from graph to graph right but
What what they do tell us is if there is a cycle and in fact
It is the case that every one of these packages in this graph is part of a cycle
And I'm
Similarly
Will we have when we have two packages here
And eat one of these packages
Is part of a cycle
Okay questions
Alright so here are the definitions of the different Edge types there's the tree as right that's
What kind of bomb is
Clear there's the package
A descendant leading to an ancestor a forward Edge is an ancestor leading to a descendant this is
Maybe you should put something in here like a Ford edges least to a descendant and is
Not
Patriot
But like you said they don't really matter the forward I just in the cross such as they don't tell us much
Okay so
Across ages an ancestor descendant that the term
Package has a different meaning when you're talking about an undirected graph and a directed graph
Goodnight you're going to see that come up a lot we're going to have the same words for these two different con
And they're going to have slightly different meanings
Okay so
Does anybody have any idea how we can tell
Whether or not an edge is a package or a
Weather not an edge of the package
Right good that's that's the biggest reason that were using pre numbers and post
Those numbers is so that we can find packages because we're going to see that it's important to
Know if there is a cycle in the graph
Because if there's no cycle in the graph then we have this thing called a dad
Directed acyclic graph and those have a lot of great properties and there's a lot of fish
Algorithms that you can do on bags that you can't do on
Just regular directed graph so it's it's in our best interest to try to see if the
Graph is a dad before we
Trying algorithm on Excel this is dumb
What is one way to do that okay so what is the formula well
I want you guys to notice a few things
A.m.
An ancestor the ancestors of pre and post numbers
Volbeat will contain all of its children's pre and post numbers
Right if you think about them as an interval for example
Let's go let's go back here instead
Let's see
H is
A descendant
Right
He is the grandfather of the h
And look at the post numbers
We have
Me
Goes from 7 to 14
NH goes from 11 to 12
See see how the The Descendants post numbers are contained as an interval
Entirely within its ancestor in one way to think about this is the whole
Stack
Idea right somebody's appearance of another vertex as a parent
Or ancestor of another text if you put that vertex in the stack put the put the descendant in and then
Take the send it out for you take the parent so if we have this idea of
Pre and post numbers
To tell whether of an edge of the back at all we have to do is see if it's
If its head
The vertex that it comes out of
I'm have pre and post numbers entirely within its tail
Vertex that goes into
Here are
The definitions of the edges in terms of their pre and post numbers but this one really is the most
Until all that means is
You
B is a package if
If you put me first into the stack then you take you out and take me out
Okay so
Just like in the class before I didn't quite get to the part of class I wanted to
You cover the homework entirely so I may be removing one of
The homework problems from the homework because
I also thought that we'd still have time to cover it before the homework was due but then I remember that we have a
Holiday this coming week so
I'll send a post out in Piazza formalizing it but what I would like you to do is
Look through the slides they're posted and look through the book it
It goes through a way of using the post numbers to linearize a tag okay so where it
We're going to cover it on Wednesday in detail but maybe this would be a nice way to
To prepare yourself for Wednesdays lecture okay have a great
Long weekend everyone
So are you