On Monday we watch the film cities on speed.
The transformation Bogut I just want to point a couple things out in there
So that is when Marcus did the
Determining dentist the disarmament programme was social and was volunteering
Social
It wasn't a lot
There was no law requiring people to turn in their guns
And then for hit For You Second Amendment fans
And then II
A second opinion oh so you know they have Columbia unfortunately has a
Okay guys can't you stop talking please
Thank you
Columbia houses
Unfortunate
Proviso that mirrors only hold office for two years soap in USA
I was really hurry to get that
Infrastructure revision
Gonna need to do
Non consultative and non-participatory way what you know
Aroused public anger so 18% support
Imagine there was
Also
Very ambitious infrastructure
Redesigned but it was carried out over
Many years and with more consultation more participation
So
What were as selfish as we discussed today I caught the sign and justice
First as law alone created
Justice now requires
Also
Social norms in support of legal obedience
Really cat the war of all against all and urban Columbia
The two weeks ago we read
A paper about
It in the poor neighborhoods of many managing where it was like Hobbes war of all against all
We would pass through
677 day and the murder rate was the highest
In the world and maybe in in modern history
I'm going to look at the construction of Justice in Bogota meta-gene which was
Had to do a three making the culture and remaking the built-in Farm
Emory going to examine evidence social psychological evidence and then
Performance evidence intention
Sporty's Hills
So first we have to consider
Alone
How's the fishing for Change and no it's not illegal centralism
The doctrine of legal centralism
Is the idea
The most places most people obey most laws
And that's true in some places like Sweden of us
But as soon as you know that's not true all over the world
Laughter
Pencil is always the best way to bring about social change and to remedy
Social hard harm so
What is there harmful social norms
You know a lot of people practice maybe the arm for the directly
I cannot just be simply outlawed
Well this is something I've worked on in theory and practice and
Ice cream criminalisation is often proposed as a remedy against harmful
Social norms like female genital cutting
Early female marriage caste discrimination
I'll give you so I'll give you an example
So early female marriages been illegal in India since 1929
And 50% of the population of girls are married under age 18
Because people
Are bad or anything or reasons for
Nearly marriage and have to address the reasons
Rose and threatening to I said you throw grandma and jail right
Any law that requires you to throw grandma and Jo is not is not going to work
I work with UNICEF UNICEF is so
There's a lot of things in one of its program system is to
Work with
Developing countries to
Establish legal ban on corporal punishment of children in school so I was in the USA
Event with a is a 60 from all over the world
Niacin
Anybody from a country where corporal punishment has been legally banned where it actually no longer
Takes place in the school's raise your hand
Hand
Everyone left and no one raised their hands because the
Because
The donor countries in United Nations
Pressure people pressure countries to pass the band they have other things to worry about
You're not giving an alternative way
Alternative methods alternate training to maintain discipline in school you're not giving out here there's just this Authority is this
You can no longer do that or will put you in jail
The song you know for changing is harmful practices but effective way so
The standard story on why people obey the law
What time is so long because there was
The law was not obeyed in Bogota and make energy
Engine
It wasn't
An important consideration in people's decisions
I saw the standard story
About why people obey the law because
One is more of a believe the authority is legitimate
The other reason is that they fear legal punishment
But seldom mention is whether or not
There's the social Norm of legal and social norms you know is informal is social is social approval
Social disapproval
So
Being motivated by social and legal businesses
You know if
You and your family would be
Horrified by the opinion of your friends and family should you be arrested and go to court for some
Criminal offense
You're eating here and concern to avoid that kind of Shame
NSN effect
And US criminology this is a summary of the
Multiple studies and there's nothing
Nothing
Later
This is the general View
Why do people obey the law
I believe that illicit conduct is wrong
That's Amore
And the fear of peer disapproval embarrassment or social stigma
Courage offending behaviour so
Is people standard story is
People bit
People by the law because they fear punishment
Empirically it turns out that
Extra legal sanctions of the moral reasons for compliance the social reasons for client
Compliance
Are much stronger than the term effect of the legal sanctions
The pedialyte with legal sanctions
Applies to a small portion of the population
Let's say that is prone to
To break the law
And the moral and social
Motivation
Arkham
Compel remainder the pop
African convinced the remainder of the population to
Halo soy
What If You observe failure to pay
Esenboga Tron the early 1990s
Why well there's no social normally would be
Andaz Napa
In some pockets of the city
There is a social number legal Defiance you were a cool dude outlaw
You know if you if you spit on the on the lawn on the place
Another reason is Sofia
New legal Norms too far from the current social Norm
Or both
Back
So
When there's no when there's no social normally go obedience illegal command to obey the law has no effect
So which of these is a no shooting sign that has the statutory
Fitness picture of excited
Hand
In the right-hand case federal law doesn't hurt anybody
You know when the new legal Norm is too far from the current social Norm
Best wind
So free sample
Wyndham
It in
Is San Diego a country I know
Many people practice polygamy both
Both because they were Muslims and part before they were Muslims
Several of the ethnic groups practice polygamy
Practice polygamy so when they became independent
And Senegal Dakar was the capital of French West Africa Senegal sophisticated number ways
Sonic on Independence in 1963
Abolished
Polygamy even though maybe 70% of populations doing it
So the laws never you know if it's ridiculous to enforce the law that somebody people Define
And
So the new legal Norm was too far from the currents
Social and what they did
When they passed a law to say
You could opt into monogamy or polygamy in the
Original marriage contract
So maybe you don't like putting me but you leave it up to free choice
You know it's a half-measure
Eruption of free choice
Hemet alts
That's a presentation I just gave your presentation I frequently
Take 2 hours to make that's a little thin but you get the idea of a social Norm
Probably going to be insane here we are
Here are some data
Homicides per hundred thousand in the three largest cities in Colombia
The blue is Mary Jane
Highest
Highest in a limit
Purple is the world average
I said
Turn on 2000
Who is Mary Jane in 9294
This is when they said they were making progress but people said well not much
And this is today and it's actually gone down
More
And this is simple guitar
Gone down a lot
And then this is Kali
Circus, until recently didn't have these transformative initiatives and
City
In part because in college
Inoculating the traditionally fused
And that blocked
I reported that blocked it kind of fun
Reformist
So I'm taking a slide
With permission from Xavier.
Who is part of this
And
So is his Doctrine was that for
For the reform you needed to
Recognizes three different systems of norms that can regulate
Citizens behaviorist legal Norms witches
Legitimacy the positive and negative reasons for complying is legitimacy of authority respect for
For the law
Or fear the authorities penalties
Moral Norms to you know
Prompted by good conscience or to avoid bad conscience
And social norms with your motive compliance is motivated by approval of others
That you care about
Or disapprove of others that you care about
And so what he did when he took office he said
People in court Bogota don't follow the law so we can't change the laws we have to change the social
Norm's first
Frozen pizza change was worse than focus on changing laws he focus on changing social
The nurse in the city
Think I'll call this the harmonization of norms
Cuz he said there shouldn't be any there should be legal Norms that
REM moral
You know that that require you to do something it's against morality so legal Norms should be
Harmonize
With moral Norms at the same time the social norms that we have
Should be should Support Compliance
With moral rules and legal rules in other words to everyone
Should be disposed
Approve socially approved or socially disapproved
Socially proof of compliance with more illegals
And if this is a
But you just can't
Cast laws and threaten to shoot people and get these
Get this to happen especially in the in this
Environment of great disorder
So here's just some examples
Hello
Law morality and
Culture are so this is social can be divorced C is culture social
So
You know it's kind of
Venn diagram
Illegally
Legally permitted in the Squarespace in the cultural and social Community ran the Morley permitted is here
So
He wanted invasive flirting is
Socially permitted and legally permitted but not morally permitted in Bogota
A very Catholic Latin American Woman
Living in a very Catholic environment goes to Miami to abort with that's legally permitted but socially
Frowned upon and morally
I found upon
I helping sight-impaired person cross the street that's legal aid Morro Bay
Socially permitted
Over paying taxes
In Bogota
That is morally and legally permitted but socially is considered so stupid and can
Contemptible how could any sane person pay more
Leo
Rape is not legally socially
Morally permitted
Escape the Room
You know the house like a
About tax or sales tax and
When you buy something from the store or street vendor
If they're keeping records that when they give you a store receipt and that's how the tax authorities keep track of things that
And that the practice was look
Hi charge you less and you don't ask me for a receipt that was so
Morally and socially permitted even though not legally permitted
Illegally selling goods and public spaces it was a huge problem
Informal construction of neighborhood had seen expropriating land setting up
Building permits
Whirling socially permitted not legally
And I'm driving a police officer
Morally and socially permitted even though
An amazing day so she encouraged
Alright so big
People
We're living in a desperate situation and they wanted way out in this is on the phone this weird guy I got elected
The song
So
Condensation or suicide are nice and moral social and legal
So he found a value that could be accepted in a
Secular
Realistic Society of life is sacred so in the movie you saw them marching in the black T-shirt La Veta Sagrada
Life is sacred and that was also
I'm a number to talk about symbolic violence this huge March
I know half a million people
Happens when
Gorillas were killing people in the city
And people were riled up and they wanted revenge and so
Who created this March so that people could
Symbolically respond to the violence
And
And I
Browns and actually responding to the violence that's driving a spiral of violence
And then the other four more motivation that he promoted Woodstock not finalized
And so this is it
Pictures of
Brian example of cultural politics in that picture he's wearing
A bulletproof vest so that's because the first four left-wing Narco gorillas
Things were going so well in Bogota that they were jealous and they wanted to discredit it so they
Intelligence found out that they were planning to assassinate Marcos
So I had to wear a bulletproof vest usually wear them here close to not let you know to keep it a secret
So he wore it over his clothes and he cut a hole over his heart
And then he had a press conference and they said
Why are you doing
I said well I have to wear this bulletproof s cuz the park is threatening to kill me
But I cut a hole in an over the heart to let them know
But I'm still willing to communicate with him and there is they're going to communicate peace will renounce file
And we can get along
And that
So embarrassed the fact that you know they were
Seriously discredited by
Hispaniola
So you say so
Try they did this sub
They use social epidemiology you know that's very strict measurement of
Morbidity and mortality
Across the territory in which causes are and they found the traffic
Traffic mortality and morbidity
Besides the criminal political violence was the greatest doing the greatest damage to people so they wanted to increase
Defiance with traffic laws
How many complied with the traffic was just
What they were born into
So how to harmonize
The campaign moral social legal so moral
If they painted the black stars wherever somebody been killed so when you come up to a busy intersection
Is a pedestrian
Can you attend UC 9 black stars
You're going to sink
Think twice
If your driver and you're rushing through
It's a reminder
And that was the
Again with Securus because the local
A local practice was putting up crosses where people were killed
Assist and officials in His official it can be really just so that
The black store
And then
They decided that one problem with traffic
With traffic is that
In traffic people are like inside these
Bigtincan sensor the normal
Social
Give me take-out face-to-face interaction is absent so
If somebody when you're walking and somebody absolutely or accident I cut you off you had to say what
Happened I say sorry sorry
Traffic when somebody cuts you off you never know where they have an excuse
Purchase location and I get extremely angry
And that's why I don't carry a gun in my car
Because I can so angry I want to kill somebody right
Immense
I'm I'm glad they're broadening the Genesee
Interchange freeway
So I mean you're still here waiting in line for like 5 minutes and some guy comes up yet
So it's a soccer and football Country Soccer countries have these red cards and white people could use in traffic
Can people use them and actually
Became part of Bogota culture and people would whip them out at parties
And they thought
And then they found that the red card
I didn't work because it was kind of fun
Led to disagreement so they created this
Another one
Hits
It's meant to be a combination of
I think I
A person lying dead on the sidewalk and a? But it's so you whip out
If somebody cuts you off or somebody does something wrong in traffic instead of the red car
Frank are you put the?
Que pasa what's going on man
Did you mean to do that what you doing social life
If somebody
If you're at a party and somebody
Play Cut and I took your plate or something you wouldn't say Hey you say
Hey you say hey you bastard give me that
Hackensack
What's going on how are you
Did you know that
And they
They fired the corrupt traffic please and as his father replace them with
Mine's initially 40 and then 400
So in a country where
So proud of dog
Would not be bothered by the police giving the traffic ticket which I would just rip up and throw on the ground
The prospect of being really killed by a clown on the street
It's just
It's something that you want to avoid if you've ever had a mine imitate you
It's the worst thing in the world
Because he
You know we're all kind of shy about who we are and all your chips and stuff paid
It's unbearable
And also
The Spanish treasury was the direct in the end Rec
So this was done downtown where everybody goes and then it's on the TV and radio and news
The whole city
But you seem what Marcus wants this for people that talk about it he and his like the public arena in and son
Every family he does something crazy so every household
In Bogota is talking about it
And the kids at dinner are saying
Mom and dad why did the crazy man put the clowns
If the
In the street
And I say well then there's like people talking about he thinks that people should have a the traffic was more and then more people
Movie alive
Getting people discuss the reasons we passed a lot so clean to build the traffic
Annalisa nothing would have happened
And I need to change some of the laws that was very
Free controversial to close down the bars at 1 a.m.
The current law
But also
I can at least
Bacon 1st 1 a.m. and then
When they got results they stand for 3 a.m.
Indirect result was tab everybody fighting about this in public like and then
Marcus and being able to say well there's all these people who died in
Gunfights and drunk driving accidents what are we going to do about it
Changing the social
So you know drunk driving used to be
Socially and legally acceptable in the Ice Age
Have you can legally unacceptable and still was somewhat socially on it
Socially acceptable
And then overtime
You know your peers would say no you can't do that
And
Look theater
Here is where so red is positive black is Colombia
Midas Bogota and so here's for those
Finishes when you're taken and here's the results
Now I'm just switch the minion
Fettuccine
And I'm sure there's lots of five minute YouTube so I'm managing I chose this one
Does the video quality is really good and also
It shows
Are the two leaders of this is not that the leaders did everything but I just want to show you that it was the result
Public public policy decisions
Physically I'm so fancy
You know that our past has a lot of things related to buy
It was written all over because of the
The answer
Silent world
Wide or solo
Narrow road or
Directions
So we decided to
What's the weather all these parties
What transformed the city of San Jose
Feeling believed in what we were doing because
Information
Comfort we have to communicate
3 days definition
We need some things about the places in the neighborhood
Usually they will say whatever you need
I'm in the theater now
The most beautiful thing you have to be
Sign
Indigo
Directions
Selena
Columbia
Okay so
The thing with the cable cars was that the poor squatted communities were at the top of the hill and it would
Would take them
They were socially culturally
Isolated the police weren't there
And building the Metro cables connected
Does a
Poor communities to the center
It was symbolic and practical inclusion
Along with the building of the spectacular
The spectacular architecture to give
To give people aspirations and hope about the
Future remedies for that
Getting started and now they can try for more
What are they doing
In Baton and Mary Jane Mary Jane
There's a monster
Restoring moral order and I'm going to
Explain that a little more in a second
Where's the Revival and creation of public spaces
They had them
Design rules now so we had to sign rules that were promoted
Consistency across the city but also allowing for
Local Variations by than just monotony
Faith
In each City they built Transportation Systems efficient transportation systems
That you made life more efficient in the 1800
Easier like in the economic sense of things being cheaper and easier but also in the symbolic sense uniting
In the margins with the center
Say Julian in Bogota they deliver it
Energy Water Sanitation transport and education to every
Last house sold before that transmission
How many households without the services
They built the Magnificent invoices a magnet schools
And then they have this combination thing with is called the library Park it's a park
Library in a crash that is a babysitting facilities
At the center or are you know what the center of the Earth
Select neighborhood
And they also transform social
One problem is when you get a certain level of violence becomes naturalized
And people don't notice it and they think it's just the way things are
Social indifference
Comes about
Empire Rap by
Why all this publicity
Name a visible traffic me and political violence criminal violence
And ways out of it
So some of the
10 comments with questions before I go on
In the Bogota
Case
A bunch of people and pay their taxes
So that end before 1991
Mirrors were appointed by
The federal government
Samir's for chest
Wheeler Dealers
So after this reform where the mirrors are directly elected the first one reform that the Bogota tax code
And then
Marcus
Undertook
Your harmonization of norms measures to increase tax compliance and tax compliance
Like doubled
And then
KUSI weather
Check the crowd and they privatize the public utility and they got a hole
Buttload of cash and he did that for the purpose of
Doing the physical transformation
And then if he saw the movie
Fitness secreta confidence
Of this city has been a mess of confidence International investors
Mercer drawing foreign investment
In the case of amazing same thing but a slower process
Building up ever greater credibility making the city more attractive to
To afford investment part of that was like
But you don't see there is like
Latin or Spanish moss education more education
So like
Everybody goes to school
Poor people get off
Free entry to tertiary school why are they doing this not just to be nice
But they have a tracking Workforce is that
Answer
The whole thing has to be coordinated you need money to write
Petco Park getting money to spell incredible is pretty stout we're no longer having 400 homicide
So they're giving a short version of some very interesting experimental literature
We know that too
If your environment where you see social norms being violated you're more likely to violate the social norms yourself
This is a nice controlled experiment everything is controlled same
Same day of the week same time same weather
So in one case
There's a sign this is
This Thread Circle means no so there's no graffiti don't write graffiti on the wall
And then you see a bunch of bicycles there and the experimenters
Put an annoying circular on the tricycle with rubber band have you ever found one circular and your body
And then
The other condition was there's no graffiti sign
And there's lots of graffiti on the wall
So
Then they measured what what happens in the first condition where there is evidence of social
Non-compliance no graffiti
People would come
Texas circular
Fold up and put in her pocket and the second condition many more people took the circular
I threw it on the ground
Trying that there can be
Spillover
Define evidence of defiance of one social Norm can spill over and cause defiance
Have another social Norm
There were about four
Similar experiments in this line providing convergent results
Later the same team 2
The opposite thing the opposite
Weather evidence of norm compliance
Would spill over
Weather evidence of compliance with one arm would spill over
To cause compliance with a separate on
And again they have like about four different
Setup San
Hi this is
They're all interesting but in this one
In the back in the very back you see somebody sweeping
So that's the treatment
A condition so in one condition somebody is doing a Public Act they're sweeping the
Sidewalk in front of their house
India and the other condition
There's nobody sleeping so
So somebody's coming down the walk and there's that the person on the left there has a bag of gross
Stamina
Person Windows subject gets near
The Confederates bills her grocery bag
And then so with a major is where the Third
Bystander the subject
Helps pick up the groceries
If she walked by
Somebody sweeping the street
She was much more likely to help
The Confederate who expelled her groceries so the idea
So this
So the idea that
You know what would happen over time and May
Meaning of showing a high level of social norm compliance
Maybe the Broken Window Theory
Please sing which doesn't have any
Which doesn't
Which is hard to measure when it's affecting the city's cuz he don't have any control
Whose experiments indicate
These mechanisms serve foot so
I study and then she go and in Senegal that this actually
Does Sam
Human rights education among other things and people say
You know the most important we have the best thing in that whole program is when we
Organize to clean the streets
You know
50 words that have to do if you can write and Sonny says what is traffic fines have to do with human rights
Was cleaning the streets first they learn Collective action with one another you know
And that spills over to being able to Collective action with another thing
Grocery stores moral order in the village they have a nice place in
I'm a pleasant place to live in visitors coming to see this is such a nice place
And I say yeah yeah we're building for a great future
So
The other remarkable things that they learned in that program this was the
The most memorable one the one that people talked about the most
Panda
Are you going to show up
Why because
In the old days you know
The stuff that people had was
Organic stuff that would rot so people would just step aside
And then you get plastic bags
Hair
All the modern detritus so in the village that doesn't Regina quick clean itself
There's just
1000 plastic bags blown everywhere and cans and
People have to adopt the new Norm of cleaning when these new products or I mean the same
So you can see
How
This is a
Is Bogota where are
Where
Where they are manifesting
You know
Social norm compliance
Kimora Lee ordered Society
That they hope it's going to spill over and the evidence says that it does and then here
And
Machine
UC
At the lower left to see the main Metro which is one of the first two actions
One of the first things that was done in this Rehabilitation
Transformation program
And then on the right you see the Metro cable cars
Which are not just for show and
Where to connect the marginal neighborhoods to the city
And then upper right you see one of the library Parks that's in
What are one of the worst most violent
Neighborhoods and left UC
Covered escalators again
So that the people at the margins
Which happened to be at the top of the ball could get down to the center transforming your life
And actually
Horns s initiate the most violent city in the world is now like a tourist destination
So
Hipster tourist like to go there and write the cable cars and they're even like
There's like two guys that were the toughest
There still problems believe me okay
Like one reason finances gone down is organized crime is reached a pact that they're not going to
You can keep the number of public murders down
Freeway
If your uterus like me you can go to community
Take the cable car Laguna 13
And I'll be the gang members in the rappers to show you around and you pay them
I don't think I'll do that I don't like to
Electronic harassment
So
I know that
Sorry you are Engineers I'm not trying to patronize you but
Hearsay evidence that
Neighborhood physical infrastructure can reduce mileage
So that's something
Best kind of consideration is something to think of InDesign so
I provided shoes
This paper it's a natural experiment they were able to match treatment neighborhoods to comfortable control neighborhoods
So the treatment was the Met installation of the Metro Cable in the spectacular infrastructure
Versus match neighborhood switch did not have that
Hand sewing
Number of violence with
Decreasing all over managing
At the same time so you need to isolate a treatment effect
That's why we have this comparison in Decline
Send the treatment areas
66% greater decline in the official homicide rate
A 75% greater decline of resident
Reports of homicide you know not all reported to the place
Desperate and also
You can take that as an indicator
He is a good indicator of
Associated provement smite
Proxy for Associated improvements and then also
Another study showed that
Access to employment opportunities Doublemint metrocable users I guess that's not surprising but
It's nice
It's always nice to find in a controlled
But I'm just saying
It was okay
And then
In both Bogota and Medellin
A systematic research
Good research design data collection guide the formation and evaluation of program
Amazing solidaria that's a city Department
Does capabilities measures of property I'm going to explain the capabilities approach
I think next week
What's the wave
It's a different way it's more objective way
Measuring
Changes in people's well-being
Rather than just their subjective happiness
Hands
They measured progress and Manga Global development indicators and
Which shows that there is
You know
Slow progress in some areas and then complete lack of progress in other areas switching forms there
Oceanside
Okay
One question if anybody has one
Okay if you want to talk to me
Track me
On the side after the class
Shark picture
Yeah right right
Like a video game